so the simplest predictor that uses
history is called the branch Target
buffer what it does is it takes the
current PC of the branch and uses that
to index into a table which we call the
btb and from this table what we read out
is our best guess for what the next PC
will be but how do we know what to put
in this table well we carry the PC of
the branch and the predicted PC
with it through the pipeline so this is
what happens at fetch later on in the
pipeline we have the correct PC new at
that point we will compare the predicted
one with the correct one and if they're
not equal we will treat that as a
misprediction and also we will use the
Branch's own PC to index again into the
btb and write this new pc that is
correct into the table so that next time
we see this Branch we get a correct
prediction as assuming that it's jumping
to the same
location but there is a problem with our
btb how big does it needs to be we want
it to in one cycle given the current PC
predict a PC so it needs to have a
single cycle latency that means we want
it to be really small however it needs
to contain an entire instruction address
let's say we're using 64-bit addressing
that means each entry is 8 bytes and we
need one entry for each possible PC from
which we can fetch the program can be
large note that an instruction can be 4
bytes yet we need eight bytes in the btb
so really the btb needs to be as large
as the program itself which is really
large so we cannot have a dedicated
entry in the btb for every possible PC
address we need the btb to be much
smaller than that how do we do that